<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="apache.html">

    &project; 

    <properties>
        <author email="mturk@apache.org">Mladen Turk</author>
        <title>Configuring Apache</title>
    </properties>

<body>

<section name="Configuration Directives">
<p>
Here are the all directives supported by Apache:
</p>
<attributes name="Directive">
<attribute name="JkWorkersFile" required="false"><p>
The name of a worker file for the Jakarta servlet containers
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkWorkerProperty" required="false"><p>
Enables setting workers.properties inside Apache configuration file.
This directive is available in jk1.2.7 version and later.
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkLogFile" required="false"><p>
Full or server relative path to the Jakarta Tomcat Connector module log file
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkMount" required="false"><p>
A mount point from a context to a Tomcat worker
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkUnMount" required="false"><p>
A no mount point from a context to a Tomcat worker
This directive is available in jk1.2.7 version and later.
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkMountCopy" required="false"><p>
Should the base server mounts be copied to the virtual server.
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkLogFile" required="false"><p>
Full or server relative path to the Jakarta Tomcat module log file
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkLogLevel" required="false"><p>
The Jakarta Tomcat module log level, can be debug, info, warn
error or trace
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkLogStampFormat" required="false"><p>
The Jakarta Tomcat Connector module <b>date</b> log format, follow strftime synthax
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkRequestLogFormat" required="false"><p>
Request log format string. See datailed description below.
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkAutoAlias" required="false"><p>
Automatically Alias webapp context directories into the Apache
document space. 
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkHTTPSIndicator" required="false"><p>
Name of the Apache environment variable that contains SSL indication
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkCERTSIndicator" required="false"><p>
Name of the Apache environment variable that contains SSL client certificates
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkCIPHERIndicator" required="false"><p>
Name of the Apache environment variable that contains SSL client cipher
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkSESSIONIndicator" required="false"><p>
Name of the Apache environment variable that contains SSL session
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkKEYSIZEIndicator" required="false"><p>
Name of the Apache environment variable that contains SSL key size in use
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkExtractSSL" required="false"><p>
Turns on SSL processing and information gathering by mod_jk
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkOptions" required="false"><p>
Set one of more options to configure the mod_jk module. See below for
deatails about this directive
</p></attribute>
<attribute name="JkEnvVar" required="false"><p>
Adds a name of environment variable that should be sent to servlet-engine
</p></attribute>

</attributes>
</section>

<section name="Configuration Directives Types">
<p>
We'll discuss here the mod_jk directive types.
</p>

<subsection name="Define workers">
<p>
<b>JkWorkersFile</b> specify the location where mod_jk will find the workers definitions.
Take a look at <a href="workers.html">Workers documentation</a> for detailed description.

<source>
  
  JkWorkersFile     /etc/httpd/conf/workers.properties
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Logging">
<p>
<b>JkLogFile</b> specify the location where mod_jk is going to place its log file.

<source>
  
  JkLogFile     /var/log/httpd/mod_jk.log
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
<b>JkLogLevel</b>
set the log level between :
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<b>info</b> log will contain standard mod_jk activity (default).
</li>
<li>
<b>warn</b> log will contain non fatal error reports.
</li>
<li>
<b>error</b> log will contain also error reports.
</li>
<li>
<b>debug</b> log will contain all information on mod_jk activity
</li>
<li>
<b>trace</b> log will contain all tracing information on mod_jk activity
</li>
</ul>

<source>  
  JkLogLevel    info
</source>

<p>
<code>info</code> should be your default selection for normal operations.
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
<b>JkLogStampFormat</b> will configure the date/time format found on mod_jk logfile. 
Using the strftime() format string it's set by<br />
default to <b>"[%a %b %d %H:%M:%S %Y]"</b>
</p>

<source>
  JkLogStampFormat "[%a %b %d %H:%M:%S %Y] "
</source>

<p>
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
<b>JkRequestLogFormat</b> will configure the format of mod_jk individual request logging. 
Request logging is configured and enabled on a per virtual host basis. 
To enable request logging for a virtual host just add a JkRequestLogFormat config. 
The syntax of the format string is similiar to the Apache LogFormat command, 
here is a list of the available request log format options:
</p>
                       
<p>
<attributes name="Options">
  <attribute name="%b" required="false">Bytes sent, excluding HTTP headers (CLF format)</attribute>
  <attribute name="%B" required="false">Bytes sent, excluding HTTP headers</attribute>
  <attribute name="%H" required="false">The request protocol</attribute>
  <attribute name="%m" required="false">The request method</attribute>
  <attribute name="%p" required="false">The canonical Port of the server serving the request</attribute>
  <attribute name="%q" required="false">The query string (prepended with a ? if a query string exists, otherwise an empty string)</attribute>
  <attribute name="%r" required="false">First line of request</attribute>
  <attribute name="%s" required="false">Request HTTP status code</attribute>
  <attribute name="%T" required="false">Request duration, elapsed time to handle request in seconds '.' micro seconds</attribute>
  <attribute name="%U" required="false">The URL path requested, not including any query string.</attribute>
  <attribute name="%v" required="false">The canonical ServerName of the server serving the request</attribute>
  <attribute name="%V" required="false">The server name according to the UseCanonicalName setting</attribute>
  <attribute name="%w" required="false">Tomcat worker name</attribute>
</attributes>

<source>
  JkRequestLogFormat     "%w %V %T"
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Forwarding">
<p>
The directive JkOptions allow you to set many forwarding options which will enable (+)
or disable (-) following option.
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
JkOptions <b>ForwardKeySize</b>,  you ask mod_jk, when using ajp13, to forward also the SSL Key Size  as 
required by Servlet API 2.3.
This flag shouldn't be set when servlet engine is Tomcat 3.2.x (on by default).

<source>  
  JkOptions     +ForwardKeySize
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
JkOptions <b>ForwardURICompat</b>, you told mod_jk to send the URI to Tomcat normally, 
which is less spec compliant but mod_rewrite compatible, 
use it for compatibility with Tomcat 3.2.x engines (on by default).

<source>  
  JkOptions     +ForwardURICompat
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
JkOptions <b>ForwardURICompatUnparsed</b>, the forwarded URI 
is unparsed, it's spec compliant but broke mod_rewrite.

<source>  
  JkOptions     +ForwardURICompatUnparsed
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
JkOptions <b>ForwardURIEscaped</b>, the forwarded URI is escaped and 
Tomcat (since 3.3 rc2) will do the decoding part.

<source>  
  JkOptions     +ForwardURIEscaped
</source>

<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
JkOptions <b>ForwardDirectories</b> is used in conjunction with <b>DirectoryIndex</b> 
directive of Apache web server. As such mod_dir should be available to Apache,
statically or dynamically (DSO)
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
When DirectoryIndex is configured, Apache will create sub-requests for
each of the local-url's specified in the directive, to determine if there is a
local file that matches (this is done by stat-ing the file).
</p>

<p>
If ForwardDirectories is set to false (default) and Apache doesn't find any
files that match, Apache will serve the content of the directory (if directive
Options specifies Indexes for that directory) or a <code>403 Forbidden</code> response (if
directive Options doesn't specify Indexes for that directory).
</p>

<p>
If ForwarDirectories is set to true and Apache doesn't find any files that
match, the request will be forwarded to Tomcat for resolution. This is used in
cases when Apache cannot see the index files on the file system for various
reasons: Tomcat is running on a different machine, the JSP file has been
precompiled etc. 
</p>

<p>Note that locally visible files will take precedence over the
ones visible only to Tomcat (i.e. if Apache can see the file, that's the one
that's going to get served). This is important if there is more then one type of
file that Tomcat normally serves - for instance Velocity pages and JSP pages.

<source>  
  JkOptions     +ForwardDirectories
</source>
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

<p>
The directive <b>JkEnvVar</b> allow you to forward an environment vars from Apache server to Tomcat engine.

<source>  
  JkEnvVar     SSL_CLIENT_V_START
</source>
<br/>
<br/>
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Assigning URLs to Tomcat">
<p>
If you have created a custom or local version of mod_jk.conf-local as noted above, 
you can change settings such as the workers or URL prefix.
</p>
<p>
<b>JkMount</b> directive assign specific URLs to Tomcat. 
In general the structure of a JkMount directive is:
</p>

<source>  
  JkMount [URL prefix] [Worker name]
</source>

<source>
  # send all requests ending in .jsp to worker1
  JkMount /*.jsp worker1
  # send all requests ending /servlet to worker1
  JkMount /*/servlet/ worker1
  # send all requests jsp requests to files located in /otherworker will go worker2
  JkMount /otherworker/*.jsp worker2
</source>

<p>
You can use the JkMount directive at the top level or inside &lt;VirtualHost&gt;
sections of your httpd.conf file.
</p>
<p><b>JkUnmount</b> directive acts as an opposite to JkMount and blocks access
to a particular URL. The purpose is to be able to filter out the particular content
types from mounted context. The following example mounts /servlet/*
context, but all .jpg files that belongs to that context are not served.
</p>
<source>
  # send all requests ending with /servlet to worker1
  JkMount /servlet/* worker1
  # do not send requests ending with .gif to worker1
  JkUnMount /servlet/*.gif worker1
</source>
<p>
JkUnMount takes precedence over JkMount directives, meaning that the JK
will first look for unmount and then for mount directives. The following
example will block all .gif files.
</p>
<source>
  # send all requests ending with /servlet to worker1
  JkUnMount /*.gif worker1
  # The .gif files will not be mouted cause JkUnMount takes
  # precedance over JkMount directive
  JkMount /servlet/*.gif worker1
</source>

<p>
<b>JkAutoAlias</b> directive automatically <b>Alias</b> webapp context directories into
the Apache document space. It enables Apache to serve a static context while Tomcat
serving dynamic context. This directive is used for convenience so that you don't
have to put an apache Alias directive for each application directory inside Tomcat's
webapp directory.
</p>

<source>
  # enter the full path to the tomcat webapps directory
  JkAutoAlias /opt/tomtact/webapps
</source>
<p>The following example shows how to serve a dynamic context by
Tomcat and static using Apache. The webapps directory has to
be accessible by apache.</p>

<source>
  # enter the full path to the tomcat webapps directory
  JkAutoAlias /opt/tomtact/webapps

  # Mount 'servlets-examples' directory. It's physical location
  # is assumed to be in the /opt/tomtact/webapps/servlets-examples
  # ajp13w is a worker defined in the workers.properties
  JkMount /servlets-examples/* ajp13w

  # Unmount desired static content from servlets-examples webapp.
  # This content will be served by the httpd directly.
  JkUnMount /servlets-examples/*.gif ajp13w
  JkUnMount /servlets-examples/*.jpg ajp13w
</source>
<p>Note that you can have a single JkAutoAlias directive per virtual
host inside your httpd.conf
</p>
<p>
<b>JkWorkerProperty</b> is a new directive available from JK 1.2.7
version. It is a convinient method for seting directives that are
usualy set insice <b>workers.propeties</b>file. The parameter for
that directive is raw line from workers.properties file.
</p>
<source>
  # Just like workers.properties but exach line is prefixed
  # with JkWorkerProperty

  # Minimal jk configuration
  JkWorkerProperty worker.list=ajp13w
  JkWorkerProperty worker.ajp13w.type=ajp13
  JkWorkerProperty worker.ajp13w.host=localhost
  JkWorkerProperty worker.ajp13w.port=8009   
</source>


</subsection>
 </section>
</body>
</document>
