<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="mturk@apache.org">Mladen Turk</author>
    <title>Changelog</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Preface">
  <p>
  This is the Changelog for Jakarta Tomcat Connectors. This changelog
  does not contain all updates and fixes to the Tomcat connectors (yet).
  It should contain fixes made only after November 10th 2004, when the
  new documentation project for JK has been started.
  </p>
</section>
<section name="Changes from JK 1.2.7">
  <br />
  <subsection name="Native">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
      Fix url rewriting by restoring the inplace uri from which the
      jsessionid was removed. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <update>
      Make load balancer algorithm thread safe by introducing mutex
      to the load balancer worker. (mturk)
      </update>
      <fix>
      Fix sending error pages for IIS to client by adding Content-Type header
      using correct api function all. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <fix>
      <bug>32696</bug>: Prevent IIS from crushing when web-inf url was requested. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <update>
      Use default cachesize for servers that support discovering the number of
      threads per child process. (mturk).
      </update>
      <fix>
      Fix Apache content-length header parsing using case insensitive compare. (billbarker) 
      </fix>
      <fix>
      Fix parsing AJP headers using case insensitive compare. (mturk) 
      </fix>
      <fix>
      Use infinite socket timeout if socket_timeout is set to zero or less then zero. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <update>
      Change <b>balanced_workers</b> to <b>balance_workers</b> but keep
      backward compatibility preserving the old directive. (mturk).
      </update>
      <fix>
      Fix ajp initialization for workers with cache_size set to zero. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <update>
      <bug>32317</bug>: Making mod_jk replication aware (Clustering Support).
      Patch provided by Rainer Jung. (mturk).
      </update>
      <fix>
      <bug>31132</bug>: Core dump when JkLogFile is missing from conf. (mturk)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Changes from JK 1.2.6">
  <br />
  <subsection name="Native">
    <changelog>
      <update>
      Added new property named recover_time that can be used to change the
      default 60 second recover time. (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
      Added custom retries for worker, so we don't depend on default setting.
      If set to a number grater then 3, it will sleep for 100ms on retry greater
      then 3 and then try again. (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
      Added JkWorkerProperty directive that enables omiting workers.properties file.
      For example: JkWorkerProperty worker.ajp13a.port=8009. (mturk)
      </update>
      <fix>
      Check all JSESSIONID cookies for a valid jvmRoute. If you have multiple Tomcats
      with overlapping domains, then you can get multiple cookies without a defined order.
      This will route correctly as long as the different domains don't have any
      Tomcats in common. (billbarker)
      </fix>
      <update>
      Added JkUnMount directive for negative mappings that works as opposite to JkMount directives.
      It is used for blocking of particular URL or content type. (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
      Added wildchar match uri mappings. One can now use JkMount to
      map /app/*/servlet/* or /app?/*/*.jsp. (mturk)      
      </update>
      <update>
      Rewrite the logging by adding Trace options. (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
      Added socket_timeout property that sets the timeout
      for the socket itself. (mturk)
      </update>
      <fix>
      Changed socket_timeout property to recycle_timeout. This better
      explains what the directive actually does. (mturk)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Changed the load balancer algorithm.
        The idea behind this new scheduler is the following:
        lbfactor is <i>how much we expect this worker to work</i>,
        or <i>the worker's work quota</i>.
        lbstatus is <i>how urgent this worker has to work to fulfill its quota
        of work</i>. We distribute each worker's work quota to the worker, and then look
        which of them needs to work most urgently (biggest lbstatus).  This
        worker is then selected for work, and its lbstatus reduced by the
        total work quota we distributed to all workers.  Thus the sum of all
        lbstatus does not change.(*)
        If some workers are disabled, the others will
        still be scheduled correctly. (mturk)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="JK 2">
<p>JK2 has been put in maintainer mode and no further development will take place.
The reason for shutting down JK2 development was the lack of developers interest.
Other reason was lack of users interest in adopting JK2, caused by configuration
complexity when compared to JK. 
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
