<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Overview</title>
<author email="jfrederic.clere@fujitsu-siemens.com">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
<author email="hgomez@apache.org">Henri Gomez</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>

<section name="What's JK ?">
<p>
<b>JK</b> is a replacement to the elderly mod_jserv. 
It was a completely new Tomcat-Apache plug-in that handles the communication between Tomcat and Apache.
</p>
<p>
The newest <b>JK2</b> is a refactoring of <b>JK</b>.
The native part has been completly
restructured and the configuration has been simplified a lot.
</p>

<p>
JK is more than just an apache module, since it could be used with majors WebServer :
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<a href="jk/aphowto.html">mod_jk</a> is an Apache module to be used with <b>Apache 1.3</b> and <b>2.0</b> Webservers.
</li>
<li>
<a href="jk/iishowto.html">isapi</a> is a redirector to be used with <b>IIS</b>.
</li>
<li>
<a href="jk/neshowto.html">nsapi</a> is a redirector to be used with <b>Netscape/iPlanet</b>.
</li>
<li>
<a href="jk/domhowto.html">dsapi</a> is a redirector to to be used with <b>Domino</b>.
</li>
</ul>

</section>

<section name="Why should I use the JK ?">
<p>
JK was develop to overcome many limitations of its ancestor, <b>mod_jserv</b>.
</p>

<p>
<b>mod_jserv</b> was too complex and because it was ported from Apache/JServ, 
it brought with it lots of JServ specific bits that aren't needed by Apache.
</p>

<p>
Where <b>mod_jserv</b> supported only Apache webservers on Unix OS, 
<b>JK</b> supports much more web servers and operating systems through 
via a compatibility layer named the <b>JK library</b>. 
The layered approach provided by the JK library makes it easier to 
support many different webservers and OS.
</p>

<p>
JK offer better support for SSL, that's was a problem with mod_jserv which couldn't 
reliably identify whether a request was made via HTTP or HTTPS. 
</p>
<p>
JK can, using the newer Ajpv13 protocol which relay many SSL informations required by servlet 2.2 and 2.3 specs.
</p>

<p>
JK offers a lot of different and flexible communications between a Web Server 
and the Tomcat Servlet Engine and could be used today with all of the ASF Tomcat Engines, 
<b>3.2.x</b>, <b>3.3.x</b>, <b>4.0.x</b>, <b>4.1.x</b> and <b>5.x</b>
</p>

</section>

<section name="What's the difference between JK and JK2 ?">
<p>
JK2 is a refactoring of JK and is much more powerfull.
</p>
<p>
Even if it works with Apache 1.3, JK2 has been developed with Apache 2.0 in mind,
and is better suited for multi-threaded servers like IIS, NES/iPlanet. It can also
be embeded in other applications and used from java.
</p>
<p>
JK2 improves the modularity and has a better separation between protocol and physical layer.
As such JK2 support fast unix-socket, and could be extended to support others communications
channels. It is better suited for JNI and may use (in a future version) JDK 1.4 NIO.
</p>
<p>
There is additional support for monitoring, similar with JMX in java. A module similar
with mod_status is provided, and additional adapters can be used to interface and 
provide status and runtime configuration. .
</p>
<p>
The configuration has been changed to follow the component models. Multiple configuration
sources can be supported ( in additon to file ) providing better integration with
the embeding application. The config layer uses the management layer APIs and it can
support persistence for changes done via runtime configuration.
</p>
<p>
Another feature is the JNI mode. Jk2 can be used as a JNI library and provide access to
native features to java. For example it provides access to shared memory ( used for 
config and monitoring in a multiprocess environment ), unix domain sockets. It can
also provide access to signals, chuid, win registry. All using the same communication
mechansim, and supporting both in-process and out-of process modes.
</p>
</section>


<section name="Are there alternative ways to connect Apache and Tomcat?">
<p>
The alternative ways are better described in <b>mod_webapp</b>
documentation.
</p>
<p>
Check <b>webapp</b> site for it and then decide if you want to go on reading. 
</p>
<p>
The big advantage of <b>mod_webapp</b> is that is very easy to configure,
has a well defined protocol named <b>WARP</b>, does not care about the old
crappy protocols used in Tomcat-3.x and so.
But it would be possible to implement the <b>WARP</b> protocol in
<b>JK2</b> ;-))
</p>
<p>
The disadvantage is that it requires the <b>Apache Portable Runtime</b>
which is still only easily available via Apache 2.0 and that it didn't support
webservers like IIS, NES/iPlanet or Domino.
</p>
</section>
</document>
