<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="doccontrib.html">

  &project;
<copyright>
   Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation
 
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
</copyright>
<properties>
<title>How to Contribute to the Documentation</title>
<author email="rsowders@usgs.gov">Robert Sowders</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Introduction">
<p>
    This document describes how you can easily contribute to the 
documentation.  I'm going to try to make it easy for everyone to help out with 
the documentation of Tomcat, more specifically the documentation for the 
connectors.  This is written from a windows user perspective as I believe they 
will most benefit from it.  For people using Unix it should be easy for them to 
apply these steps.  Just substitute Unix sytax where needed.
</p>
<p>
    The documentation is produced using xml with xsl style sheets.  This 
effectivly seperates the content of the documents from the style, so all that 
contributers need to worry about the content.  It is much easier to use than 
html.
</p>
<p>
    It's all really quite simple.  Here is what you will need:
<ul>
<li>
<b>A recent version of Ant</b>
</li>
<li>
<b>The source code for the connectors from cvs</b>
</li>
<li>
<b>Any ascii text editor</b>
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>
<section name="Getting Started Step by Step">
<p>
    After you get these tools they are simple to set up.
</p>
    <subsection name="STEP 1. Get Ant">
<p>
    Install <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Ant</a>. The only advice I 
have is to choose a simple installation path.  Now set an environment variable 
for ANT_HOME, and then add the location of the Ant/bin directory to your PATH 
variable.  Consult your Operating system documentation for information on how 
to do this.  When you are finished verify that you can run ant from the command 
line.
</p>
<p>
    Ant is used to build the documentation, among other things, and it must be 
able to see a file called <b>build.xml</b>.  This file is located in the 
<b>CVS_HOME\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk</b> directory.  In the 
<b>build.xml</b> file there is a target named docs that will be used to build 
the docs.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="STEP 2.  Get the sources">
<p>
    Get the sources for <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-tomcat-
connectors/">jakarta-tomcat-connectors</a> from the CVS repository.  If you'll 
be editing from a windows platform you will need a windows cvs client.  There 
are several available.  I like <a href="http://www.cygwin.com/">cygwin</a>.  
During the install open the developer group and click on cvs.  Unix users 
should install the CVS client of their choice, if they don't already have one.
</p>
<p>
    You are ready to download the sources now.  Change directory to the 
location where you want your repository to be, and run the following commands 
to download the sources for the first time.  For simplicity we will call this 
your <b>CVS_HOME.</b>  Mine is located in C:\build.
</p>
<p>
    Login to the repository and then give the cvs password <b>anoncvs</b>.
<screen>
<read> </read>
<read>C:\build></read>
<read>C:\build\>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic 
login</read>
<read>cvs password:  anoncvs</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    When your prompt comes back you are logged in.  Now run the following 
command to <b>checkout</b> the sources for the first time.  You should only 
need to do this once.
<screen>
<read> </read>
<read>C:\build\>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout 
jakarta-tomcat-connectors</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    You should now be watching all the downloads come in.  Now that you have 
the sources on your machine the hard part if over.  From now on, to update your 
sources all you have to do is cd into any directory in your repository and run 
cvs update
    <screen>
<note>    To update your xdocs directory simply cd into the xdocs directory 
and:</note>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\>cd xdocs</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs\>cvs update -dP</read>
</screen>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="STEP 3.  Test your build environment">
<p>
    Open a command prompt window and cd to the directory where you downloaded 
the source.  Now cd into the jk directory so <b>Ant</b> can see the 
<b>build.xml</b> file and,  from a command prompt, run the following:
<screen>
<read> </read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors>cd jk</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk>ant docs</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>.
<p>
    You should see the ant compiler messages scrolling by rapidly and then stop 
with the following:
<screen>
<read>[style] Transforming into C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-
connectors\jk\build\docs></read>
<read>[style] Processing C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs\faq.xml 
to</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\build\docs\faq.html</read>
<read>[style] Loading stylesheet C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-
connectors\jk\xdocs\style.xsl</read>
<read>[style] Processing C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs\index.xml 
to</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\build\docs\index.html</read>
<read>[copy] Copying 8 files to C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-
connectors\jk\build\docs</read>
<read> </read>
<read>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</read>
<read>Total time: 10 seconds</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk</read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    All the xml files present in the xdocs directory structure were transformed 
to html and copied to the <b>CVS_HOME\jk\docs</b> directory.  Open one of the 
html files in your browser and see how it looks.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="STEP 4.   The editing process.">
<p>
    I find it easier to use two windows while doing my updates.  One I call my 
<b>build</b> window.  I keep this one in the <b>CVS_HOME\jk</b> directory and I 
only run two commands in this window:
<screen>
<read> </read>
<note>   First I run</note>
<read>ant clean</read>
<note>   Then I run</note>
<read>ant docs</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    My second window I call my <b>edit</b> window and I keep that one in the 
<b>CVS_HOME\jk\xdocs</b> directory where I'm doing my edits, diffs, and cvs 
updates.
</p>
<p>
    Before you start editing you should always update your local repository to 
prevent conflicts.
<screen>
<note>    You only need to update the xdocs directory</note>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk>cd xdocs</read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs></read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs>cvs update -dP</read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    Now that your repository is up to date you can begin editing.  Find 
something in the documentation to edit.  When you find somethng remember the 
name of the file.  In your <b>edit</b> window find and edit the xml source file 
with the same name.  After you are done return to the  <b>build</b> window, and 
in the <b>CVS_HOME\jk</b> directory run:
<screen>
<read> </read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk> ant clean</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    This will delete all the previous html files and make the area ready for 
updated material.  Now to make fresh documents that incorporate your changes 
run:
<screen>
<read> </read>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\>ant docs</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    Use your browser to view the edits you just made, they will be in the 
<b>CVS_HOME\jk\build\docs</b> sub-tree.  If it looks good and is ready to go, 
all that is left to do is to create a patch and submit it.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="STEP 5.  Creating a patch and submitting it.">
<p>
    From your <b>edit</b> window cd into the directory that contains the xml 
file you are working on, and run the <b>cvs update</b> command.  For example, 
to produce a unified diff of the index.xml file and call it patch.txt, you 
would cd into the directory containing the index.xml file and:
<screen>
<read>C:\build\jakarta-tomcat-connectors\jk\xdocs\>cvs diff -u index.xml >  
patch.txt.</read>
<read> </read>
</screen>
</p>
<p>
    Now that you have your patch you are ready to send it in.
</p>
<p>
    Patches to the documentation are handled just like a bug report.  You 
should submit your patches to <a 
href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/">http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/</a>
 and include a good one line subject.  If this is your first time to use the 
bug database then you should read  <a 
href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/bugwritinghelp.html">http://nagoya.apach
e.org/bugzilla/bugwritinghelp.html.</a>  You will need to create a user 
account.  At the web site paste your patch into the web form and don't forget 
to describe what it is your patch is for.  Sooner or later a someone with 
commit privileges will review your suggestion.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="CVS Basics">
<p>
    After you have checked out the sources the first time it is much easier to 
use CVS.  You can cd into any directory of the repository and run <b>cvs 
update -dP</b> to get the latest sources for that directory.  For editing 
purposes you should always update your repository before you start editing to 
reduce conflicts.
</p>
<p>
    You will need to run <b>cvs diff</b> to generate patches for submission.  
Again cd into the directory containing the file you are editing and run <b>cvs 
diff -u name_of_the_file_you_edited  patch.txt</b> to generate a patch for 
submission.  The <b>-u</b> is the flag for a unified diff which is the prefered 
type.
</p>
<p>
    Pay attention to the terminal window during the update.
</p>
<p>
    Lines begining with a <b>P</b> mean the local copy was patched to update it 
to the current version in the master repository.
</p>
<p>
    Lines begining with a <b>M</b> mean your local copy is different from the 
master copy, and the changes were successfully merged into your copy.
</p>
<p>
    Lines begining with a <b>C</b> mean there was a conflict in merging the 
changes and you need to review the file and merge the changes manually.  Search 
for  >>>> and merge the changes.
</p>
<p>
    Lines begining with a <b>?</b> indicate files that reside on your local 
system which are not part of the repository.  You will normally see this when 
you are creating new files for submission.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Guides and Resources">
<p>
    A little help to get you if you need it
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.xml.org/xml/resources_focus_beginnerguide.shtml">XML 
Beginner's Guide</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/bugwritinghelp.html">Bugzilla Bug 
Writing Guide</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Ant</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.cvshome.org/">CVS Home</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-tomcat-connectors/jk/xdocs/">JK 
Docs CVS</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
</body>
</document>
