<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="workers.html">

  &project;
<copyright>
   Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation
 
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
</copyright>
<properties>
<title>Workers HowTo</title>
<author email="hgomez@apache.org">Henri Gomez</author>
<author email="shachor@il.ibm.com">Gal Shachor</author>
<author email="mturk@apache.org">Mladen Tur</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Introduction">
<p>
A Tomcat worker is a Tomcat instance that is waiting to execute servlets on behalf of some web server. 
For example, we can have a web server such as Apache forwarding servlet requests to a 
Tomcat process (the worker) running behind it.
</p>
<p>
The scenario described above is a very simple one; 
in fact one can configure multiple Tomcat workers to serve servlets on 
behalf of a certain web server. 
The reasons for such configuration can be:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
We want different contexts to be served by different Tomcat workers to provide a 
development environment where all the developers share the same web server but own a Tomcat worker of their own.
</li>
<li>
We want different virtual hosts served by different Tomcat processes to provide a 
clear separation between sites belonging to different companies.
</li>
<li>
We want to provide load balancing, meaning run multiple Tomcat workers each on a 
machine of its own and distribute the requests between them.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
There are probably more reasons for having multiple workers but I guess that this list is enough...
Tomcat workers are defined in a properties file dubbed workers.properties and this tutorial 
explains how to work with it.
</p>

<p>
This document was originally part of <b>Tomcat: A Minimalistic User's Guide</b> written by Gal Shachor, 
but has been split off for organizational reasons. 
</p>
</section>

<section name="Defining Workers">
<p>
Defining workers to the Tomcat web server plugin can be done using a properties file 
(a sample file named workers.properties is available in the conf/ directory).
</p>

<p>
the file contains entries of the following form:
</p>

<p>
<b>worker.list</b>=&lt;a comma separated list of worker names&gt;
</p>

<source>
  # the list of workers
  worker.list= worker1, worker2
</source>

<p>
When starting up, the web server plugin will instantiate the workers whose name appears in the 
<b>worker.list</b> property, these are also the workers to whom you can map requests.
</p>

<subsection name="Workers Type">
<p>
Each named worker should also have a few entries to provide additional information on his behalf.
This information includes the worker's type and other related worker information. 
Currently the following worker types that exists are (JK 1.2.5):
</p>

<table>
  <tr><th>Type</th><th>Description</th></tr>
  <tr><td>ajp12</td><td>This worker knows how to forward requests to out-of-process Tomcat workers using the ajpv12 protocol.</td></tr>
  <tr><td>ajp13</td><td>This worker knows how to forward requests to out-of-process Tomcat workers using the ajpv13 protocol.</td></tr>
  <tr><td>jni</td><td>This worker knows how to forward requests to in-process Tomcat workers using JNI.</td></tr>
  <tr><td>lb</td><td>This is a load-balancing worker; it knows how to provide round-robin based sticky load balancing with a certain level of fault-tolerance.</td></tr>
</table>

<p>
Defining workers of a certain type should be done with the following property format:
</p>

<p>
<b>worker</b>. <b>worker name</b>.<b>type</b>=&lt;worker type&gt;
Where worker name is the name assigned to the worker and the worker type is one of the four types defined 
in the table (a worker name may not contain any space (a good naming convention for queue named should 
follow the Java variable naming rules).
</p>

<source>
  # Defines a worker named "local" that uses the ajpv12 protocol to forward requests to a Tomcat process.
  worker.local.type=ajp12
  # Defines a worker named "remote" that uses the ajpv13 protocol to forward requests to a Tomcat process.
  worker.remote.type=ajp13
  # Defines a worker named "fast" that uses JNI to forward requests to a Tomcat process.
  worker.fast.type=jni
  # Defines a worker named "loadbalancer" that loadbalances several Tomcat processes transparently.
  worker.loadbalancer.type=lb
</source>

</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Setting Worker Properties">
<p>
After defining the workers you can also specify properties for them. 
Properties can be specified in the following manner:
</p>

<p>
worker.&lt;worker name&gt;.&lt;property&gt;=&lt;property value&gt;
</p>

Each worker has a set of properties that you can set as specified in the following subsections:

<subsection name="ajp12 Worker properties">
<p>
The ajp12 typed workers forward requests to out-of-process Tomcat workers 
using the ajpv12 protocol over TCP/IP sockets.
</p>

<p>
the ajp12 worker properties are :
</p>

<p>
<b>host</b> property set the host where the Tomcat worker is listening for ajp12 requests.
</p>

<p>
<b>port</b> property set The port where the Tomcat worker is listening for ajp12 requests
</p>

<p>
<b>lbfactor</b>property is used when working with a load balancer worker, this is the load-balancing factor for the worker.
We'll see more on this in the lb worker section.
</p>

<source>
  # worker "worker1" will talk to Tomcat listening on machine www.x.com at port 8007 using 2.5 lb factor
  worker.worker1.host=www.x.com
  worker.worker1.port=8007
  worker.worker1.lbfactor=2.5
</source>

<p>
Notes: In the ajpv12 protocol, connections are created, used and then closed at each request.
The default port for ajp12 is 8007
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="ajp13 Worker properties">
<p>
The ajp13 typed workers forward requests to out-of-process Tomcat workers using the ajpv13 protocol over TCP/IP sockets.
The main difference between ajpv12 and ajpv13 are that:
<ul>
<li>
ajpv13 is a more binary protocol and it try to compress some of the request data by coding 
frequently used strings as small integers.
</li>
<li>
ajpv13 reuse open sockets and leaves them open for future requests (remember when you've got a Firewall between your 
WebServer and Tomcat).
</li>
<li>
ajpv13 has special treatment for SSL information so that the container can implement 
SSL related methods such as isSecure().
</li>
</ul>

</p>

<p>
You should note that Ajp13 is now the only out-process protocol supported by Tomcat 4.0.x, 4.1.x and 5.
</p>


<source>
  # worker "worker2" will talk to Tomcat listening on machine www2.x.com at port 8009 using 3 lb factor
  worker.worker2.host=www2.x.com
  worker.worker2.port=8009
  worker.worker2.lbfactor=3
  # worker "worker2" use up to 10 sockets, which will stay no more than 10mn in cache
  worker.worker2.cachesize=10
  worker.worker2.cache_timeout=600
  # worker "worker2" ask operating system to send KEEP-ALIVE signal on the connection
  worker.worker2.socket_keepalive=1
  # worker "worker2" want ajp13 connection to be dropped after 5mn (recycle)
  worker.worker2.recycle_timeout=300
</source>

<p>
Notes: In the ajpv13 protocol, the default port is 8009
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="lb Worker properties">
<p>
The load-balancing worker does not really communicate with Tomcat workers.
Instead it is responsible for the management of several "real" workers. 
This management includes:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
Instantiating the workers in the web server.
</li>
<li>
Using the worker's load-balancing factor, perform weighed-round-robin load balancing where 
high lbfactor means stronger machine (that is going to handle more requests)
</li>
<li>
Keeping requests belonging to the same session executing on the same Tomcat worker.
</li>
<li>
Identifying failed Tomcat workers, suspending requests to them and instead fall-backing on 
other workers managed by the lb worker.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
The overall result is that workers managed by the same lb worker are load-balanced (based on their lbfactor and current user session) and also fall-backed so a single Tomcat process death will not "kill" the entire site.
The following table specifies properties that the lb worker can accept:
<ul>
<li><b>balanced_workers</b> is a comma separated list of workers that the load balancer need to manage. 
These workers should not appear in the worker.list property.</li>
<li><b>sticky_session</b> specifies whether requests with SESSION ID's should be routed back to the same
Tomcat worker. If sticky_session is an int and is not 0 it is set to JK_TRUE and sessions are sticky, otherwise
sticky_session is set to false. Set sticky_session to JK_FALSE when Tomcat is using a Session Manager which
can persist session data across multiple instances of Tomcat. By default sticky_session is set to JK_TRUE.</li>
</ul>
</p>

<source>
   The worker balance1 while use "real" workers worker1 and worker2
  worker.balance1.balanced_workers=worker1, worker2
</source>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Advanced lb Worker properties">
<p>
With JK 1.2.x, new load-balancing and fault-tolerant support has been added via
2 new properties, <b>local_worker_only</b> and <b>local_worker</b>.
</p>

<p>
Let's take an example environment:
</p>

<p>
A cluster with two nodes (worker1+worker2), running a webserver + tomcat tandem on each node and 
a loadbalancer in front of the nodes.
</p>

<source>
  # The advanced router LB worker
  worker.list=router
  # Define a 'local_worker' worker using ajp13
  worker.worker1.port=8009
  worker.worker1.host=node1.domain.org
  worker.worker1.type=ajp13
  worker.worker1.lbfactor=1
  worker.worker1.local_worker=1
  # Define another 'local_worker' worker using ajp13
  worker.worker2.port=8009
  worker.worker2.host=node2.domain.org
  worker.worker2.type=ajp13
  worker.worker2.lbfactor=1
  worker.worker2.local_worker=0
  # Define the LB worker
  worker.router.type=lb
  worker.router.balanced_workers=worker1,worker2
  worker.router.local_worker_only=1
</source>

<p>
The <b>local_worker</b> flag on worker1 and worker2 tells the <b>lb_worker</b> which connections are going 
to the local worker. 
</p>


</subsection>


<subsection name="Property file macros">
<p>
You can define "macros" in the property files. 
These macros let you define properties and later on use them while 
constructing other properties and it's very usefull when you want to
change your Java Home, Tomcat Home or OS path separator
</p>

<source>
  # property example, don't hardcode path separator
  ps=\
  workers.tomcat_home=d:\tomcat
  workers.java_home=d:\sdk\jdk1.2.2
  # Using macros we'll have : worker.inprocess.class_path=d:\tomcat\classes
  worker.inprocess.class_path=$(workers.tomcat_home)$(ps)classes
  # Using macros we'll have : worker.inprocess.class_path=d:\sdk\jdk1.2.2\lib\tools.jar
  worker.inprocess.class_path=$(workers.java_home)$(ps)lib$(ps)tools.jar
</source>

</subsection>

</section>

<section name="A sample worker.properties">
<p>
Since coping with worker.properties on your own is not an easy thing to do, 
a sample worker.properties file is bundled along JK. 
</p>

<p>
You could also find here a sample workers.properties defining :
</p>

<ul>
<li>
An ajp12 worker that used the host localhost and the port 8007
</li>
<li>
An ajp13 worker that used the host localhost and the port 8008
</li>
<li>
A jni worker
</li>
<li>
A lb worker that load balance the ajp12 and ajp13 workers
</li>
</ul>

<source>
  # Define some properties
  workers.apache_log=/var/log/httpd/
  workers.tomcat_home=/var/tomcat3
  workers.java_home=/opt/IBMJava2-131/
  ps=/
  # Define 4 workers, 3 real workers using ajp12, ajp13, jni, the last one being a loadbalancing worker 
  worker.list=worker1, worker2, worker3, worker4
  # Set properties for worker1 (ajp12)
  worker.worker1.type=ajp12
  worker.worker1.host=locahost
  worker.worker1.port=8007
  worker.worker1.lbfactor=5
  # Set properties for worker2 (ajp13)
  worker.worker2.type=ajp13
  worker.worker2.host=locahost
  worker.worker2.port=8009
  worker.worker2.lbfactor=50
  worker.worker2.cachesize=10
  worker.worker2.cache_timeout=600
  worker.worker2.socket_keepalive=1
  worker.worker2.socket_timeout=300
  # Set properties for worker3 (jni)
  worker.worker3.type=jni
  # Set worker3 bridge type, here Tomcat 3.3
  worker.worker3.bridge=tomcat33
  # Set worker3 classpath
  worker.worker3.class_path=$(workers.tomcat_home)$(ps)classes
  worker.worker3.class_path=$(workers.tomcat_home)$(ps)lib$(ps)tomcat.jar
  # Set worker3 tomcat command line
  worker.worker3.cmd_line=-home
  worker.worker3.cmd_line=$(workers.tomcat_home)
  # Set worker3 Tomcat/JVM settings
  worker.worker3.jvm_lib=$(workers.java_home)$(ps)jre$(ps)bin$(ps)classic$(ps)libjvm.so
  worker.worker3.stdout=$(workers.apache_log)$(ps)inprocess.stdout
  worker.worker3.stderr=$(workers.apache_log)$(ps)inprocess.stderr
  worker.worker3.sysprops=tomcat.home=$(workers.tomcat_home)
  # Set properties for worker4 (lb) which use worker1 and worker2
  worker.worker4.balanced_workers=worker1,worker2
</source>

</section>
</body>
</document>
