<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document title="WARP 1.0 (draft)">
  <description>
    The WARP protocol version 1.0 (draft)
  </description>

  <section title="Introduction">
    <description>
      An overview of the WARP protocol
    </description>

    <p>
      WARP was inspired by the great effort made by the Apache JServ team
      in finding an efficent transport protocol allowing to connect over a
      reliable full-duplex transmission channel (such as TCP over IP,
      bi-directional pipes or UNIX sockets) a servlet container and an
      HTTP protocol stack (normally, a web server).
    </p>

    <p>
      Note, this revision of the WARP protocol has not been adopted yet by
      the <b>WebApp module</b> for the Apache Web Server or by <b>Apache
      Tomcat</b>.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="The WARP name">
    <description>
      Maximum WARP, engage! (Tales about a name)
    </description>

    <p>
      First of all, for non science fiction fanatics, WARP is an acronym and
      means, (to use a syntax similar to Perl regular expressions) "Web
      Application Remote (Access|Control)+ Protocol".
    </p>

    <p>
      In "Star Trek" terms, WARP is a measuring unit for speed, such as
      "miles per hour" or "meters per seconds". Always in "Star Trek" terms,
      <b>Radio Free Tomorrow</b> gives us a very nice description about what
      exactly the term "WARP" means (you can see the full text
      <a href="http://rft.melm.org/story/2002/3/25/182619/336">here</a>):
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        [...] Warping space as a means of traveling faster than light is a
        method based in solid fact, and physicists have devised a mathematical
        model of the universe which would allow it to work.
        <br/>
        The idea behind warp drive is this: you bend a small section of space
        to the extent that it completely encloses your starship, effectively
        isolating it from the outside universe. You then move this isolated
        pocket of space time to your destination, and allow it to rejoin normal
        space.
        <br/>
        Because it's not moving through normal physical space, the lightspeed
        limit doesn't apply to the warp. It can travel as fast as you want it
        to. And because space itself is being bent, the starship technically
        isn't moving at all, so restrictions on normal Newtonian motion don't
        affect it.
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      In other terms, then, WARP is all about "bending" something (space), to
      allow something else (the spaceship) to move faster from one point to
      another.
    </p>

    <p>
      How does this applies to our case? Given that we can't "bend" your OS
      kernel to transmit data faster over a reliable full-duplex connection,
      neither we can "bend" the data included into the HTTP request to be
      transmitted from one point to another, the WARP protocol "bends" the
      rules of HTTP, transmitting an HTTP request, with all operational data
      attached to it, into a different and more efficent manner, to minimize
      the computational time required by both parties to process it.
    </p>

    <p>
      To simplify, although HTTP version 1.1 is a great protocol for hypertext
      data, it is not suited to encapsulate a pre-parsed half-processed HTTP
      request and transmit it to another party for further elaboration.
    </p>

    <p>
      And by all means, we hope that when you fire up your servlet container,
      you won't stand up in your cubicle sticking your index finger out and
      screaming "Maximum WARP, engage!".
    </p>
  </section>
</document>
