<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Configuration in the Web Server</title>
<author email="cmanolache@yahoo.com">Costin Manolache</author>
<author email="jfrederic.clere@fujitsu-siemens.com">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>
    <section name="Intro">
        <p>Jk2 uses a config file ( workers2.properties ) in the style of a .properties or ini
 file. It can be configured to use any other backend that provides similar
 capabilities.
  </p>
        <p>
  This document describes the format of this configuration file. Its default name is ${serverRoot}/conf/workers2.properties,
  where ${serverRoot} is something like /opt/apache.
</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Config file">
        <p> The default config file is user editable, but mod_jk will persist the 
changes requested by protocol( not implemented). If you manually change the file while jk2 is 
working, your changes will be lost. 
  </p>
        <p>The default configuration format . .  Each setting consists of an object 
name and a property, with the associated value. The property name is a simple
 string, with no '.' in it. The name can be anything, but it must have a
known  'type' as prefix.  
  </p>
        <p>2 formats are supported:   
            <source>
                TYPE:NAME.PROPERTY=VALUE 
            </source>
        </p>
        <p>and
            <source>
                [TYPE:NAME]
                PROPERTY=VALUE
            </source>
        </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Components"><p>Each component instance has a name, that is used for configuration and at runtime. Each component has a number of configurable properties. The following rules are used:
<ul><li>The name is composed from the type and a local part, separated with a ':' ( example: channel.unixsocket:/tmp/jk.socket ) </li>
<li>The 'type' consist of '.' and ascii characters.  It is mapped to a JMX 'domain'.  </li>
<li>The local part consists of ascii characters and .:/; 
<p>Note that '=,' are not currently allowed - a future version may support the jmx syntax by using quotes to separate the local part from the property and value ( in .properties mode we must use '=' to separate the value from type, local name and property name ). </p></li>
<li>The property is a simple name, with no dots. </li>
<li>A simple form of substitution is used in values, where $(property) will be replaced with a previously defined setting. If the property has ':' in it, it'll take the value from the object, if not it'll take the value from a global map.</li></ul></p>
        <subsection name="Common properties">
            <p>Common properties for all components</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>disabled</td>
                        <td>0 (false)</td>
                        <td>"disabled" state for the component, 1=true 0=false</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>debug</td>
                        <td>0 (false)</td>
                        <td>"debug" state for the component, 1=true 0=false</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="workerEnv">
            <p>This component represent the core jk2, it has the default logger for all other components. Is the central controller, it controls global properties
and  provides access to all other objects</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>logger</td>
                        <td>logger</td>
                        <td>Default loger used by jk2 components, can be changed in the config file, normally it defaults to "logger" the Alias for the default logger for the Server/platform.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>timing</td>
                        <td>0</td>
                        <td>Will jk2 get request timing (needs APR?)</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="config">
            <p>The config component, hold the detail of the conifg system, such config file name, create global defines</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>debugEnv</td>
                        <td>0</td>
                        <td>Set the debug level of the hidden env component </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="uriMap"/>
        <subsection name="shm">
            <p>Shared memory descriptor</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>file</td>
                        <td>No default value</td>
                        <td>Name of the file that will be mmapped to use as shared memory.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>size</td>
                        <td>No default value</td>
                        <td>Size of the file.</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="uri">
            <p>A uri stores a pattern that is used
 to match requests to workers, and asociated properties</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>worker</td>
                        <td>lb:0 (The default loadbalancer)</td>
                        <td>Name of the worker that process the request corresponding to the uri</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>context</td>
                        <td/>
                        <td>the context that will be served by this uri component (webapp style)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>reverse</td>
                        <td>0</td>
                        <td>If set to 1 all satisfied matches will be rejected.
This is usefull for the situations when you wish to map the entire application, but still wish that
paticular context is not served through Tomcat.</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="vm">
            <p>Represents the JVM when used as inprocess container
            </p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>JVM</td>
                        <td>(Autoguess)</td>
                        <td>JVM to use for this vm</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>OPT</td>
                        <td/>
                        <td>Option to pass to this vm, this is a multivalued property</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="channels">
            <p>A channel represents a transport protocol, connecting 2
sides  for RPC communication. The most common and standard is the tcp socket.
Other  important  channels are unix socket and jni</p>
            <subsection name="channel.un">
                <p>
    AF_UNIX socket. Only on UNIX like platform. These sockets are faster
    than "normal" sockets but they are limited to the machine. 
</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>file</td>
                            <td>Name of socket</td>
                            <td>Name of the socket file (It is created by the Tomcat ChannelUn)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="channel.socket">
                <p>
    A communication transport to a remote Engine
    <b>Magic:</b> The local part of the name will be the Engine name,
    to use when defining the uri mappings. For example
    channel.socket.local_9009 will automatically define an engine named
    local_9009, and if no other setting is set ajp13 will be used for
    communication.
    <b>Magic:</b> If no channel is defined in the config, a default channel
    will be constructed with port=8009, engine=DEFAULT, worker=ajp13 -
    named 'channel.socket.DEFAULT'
</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>port</td>
                            <td>8009</td>
                            <td>Port where Tomcat is listening</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>host</td>
                            <td>localhost</td>
                            <td>Remote host</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>keepalive</td>
                            <td>0</td>
                            <td>? </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>lbfactor</td>
                            <td>1</td>
                            <td>
    Load balancing factor to use. At this moment, it'll be set on the worker,
    but in future it should be possible to use lb on a channel level.
  </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>group</td>
                            <td>lb:0</td>
                            <td>loadbalanced groups to which this channel and the associated worker will be added, multivalued</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>tomcatId</td>
                            <td>?</td>
                            <td>?</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="channel.jni">
                <p>The jni channel, used if tomcat is started inprocess</p>
            </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="workers">
            <p>
             For the moment 4 worker types are supported: worker.jni,ajp13,status,lb.
            </p>
            <subsection name="worker.jni">
                <p>worker used in inprocess, holds the details of the Tomcat class to startup, and paramters to pass</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>class</td>
                            <td>org/apache/jk/apr/TomcatStarter</td>
                            <td>class that holds the main method called to start tomcat</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>ARG</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>Arguments to pass to main method when called</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>stdout</td>
                            <td>NULL</td>
                            <td>file to redirect Standard output from the java process</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>stderr</td>
                            <td>NULL</td>
                            <td>file to redirect Standard output from the java process </td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="ajp13">
                <p>Default worker</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>secretkey</td>
                            <td>NULL</td>
                            <td>
                                <b>Magic:</b> The secret key will be set automatically on the associated
    worker.
  </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>tomcatId</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>route</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>group</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>level</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>channel</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="status">
                <p>Worker that outputs a page with usefull information to monitor JK2</p>
                <p>To use it add a uri component assigned to this worker</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="lb">
                <p>Loadbalanced worker</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>worker</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>noWorkerMsg</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>noWorkerCode</td>
                            <td>503</td>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>hwBalanceErr</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="loggers">
            <p>Any connector based on jk2, at least has a default logger, that can be reached using the "logger" alias, the logger used is the more appropiate for the plataform/server combination, Apache2 under in any platform has logger.apache2 as default, IIS on his only platform uses logger.win32, and Any apache 1 install uses logger.file as default.., the config file lets you change that defaults, you can end using logger.file in IIs i.e</p>
            <p>The properties shared by all loggers are:
<table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property name</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>level</td>
                        <td>INFO</td>
                        <td>Log level. Supported: EMERG, ERROR, INFO, DEBUG</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
            <subsection name="logger.file">
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property name</th>
                            <th>Default</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>file</td>
                            <td>${serverRoot}/logs/jk2.log</td>
                            <td>
    Log file.  XXX you may be able to change this at runtime,
               to implement rolling.
  </td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="logger.win32">
                <p>logger used in the IIS server by default, it ends at native Application Event Log.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="logger.apache2">
                <p>Logger used in Apache2 servers, it normally in ends in error.log </p>
            </subsection>
        </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Examples">
        <p>
The examples below are working when the Tomcat is configured according the 
examples described in the configtc file.
</p>
        <subsection name="/example using normal socket">
            <p> 
Map /examples to the Tomcat /examples context using a normal socket. Note the 
IP instead localhost (The JVM listens on the IPV4 address not no the IPV6).
</p>
            <p>
                <source>
[shm]
file=${serverRoot}/logs/shm.file
size=1048576

# Example socket channel, override port and host.
[channel.socket:localhost:8019]
port=8019
host=127.0.0.1

# define the worker
[ajp13:localhost:8019]
channel=channel.socket:localhost:8019

# Uri mapping
[uri:/examples/*]
worker=ajp13:localhost:8019
</source>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="/jkstatus">
            <p>
Map /jkstatus to the status worker.
</p>
            <p>
                <source>
[shm]
file=${serverRoot}/logs/shm.file
size=1048576

# define the worker
[status:status]

# Uri mapping
[uri:/jkstatus/*]
worker=status:status
</source>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="/example using AF_UNIX socket">
            <p>
Map /examples to the Tomcat /examples context using a AF_UNIX socket.
Socket file is create by the Tomcat becarefull when the Web Server runs in
a different user than the Tomcat with the permission of the socket file:
<source>
apache20@jfcexpert:~/apache> ls -l /home1/jakarta/jakarta-tomcat-4.1/dist/work/jk2.socket
srw-rw----    1 jakarta  jakarta         0 Jun 20 08:27 /home1/jakarta/jakarta-tomcat-4.1/dist/work/jk2.socket
</source>
Here the Tomcat user and the Web Server user must be in the same group.
</p>
            <p>
                <source>
[shm]
file=${serverRoot}/logs/shm.file
size=1048576

# Example unixsocket channel.
[channel.un:unixsocket]
file=/home1/jakarta/jakarta-tomcat-4.1/dist/work/jk2.socket

# define the worker
[ajp13:unixsocket]
channel=channel.un:unixsocket

# Uri mapping
[uri:/examples/*]
worker=ajp13:unixsocket
</source>
            </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</document>
