<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Installation of jk2 in the Web Server</title>
<author email="jfrederic.clere@fujitsu-siemens.com">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>
  <section name="Installation">
    <p>
      The actual build mechanism creates the dso files in the
      build/jk2/${servername} subdirectory of the jakarta-tomcat-connectors/jk.
      When configure --with-jni is used 2 dso files are created.
      These files have to be copied in the right location of the web server
      installation.
    </p>
    <p>
      JNI support in JK2 require APR, which is provded in Apache 2.0, and is
      available for many platforms, so Apache 1.3, IIS and NES/iPlanet should be
      able to use it
    </p>
    <subsection name="Apache 1.3">
      <p>
        In the following example Apache-1.3 is installed in
        /home/apache13/ and the commands are executed in
        the jakarta-tomcat-connectors directory.
      </p>
      <p>
        Apache 1.3 require APR, and if APR has been built with pthread support
        and your Apache 1.3 wasn't (general case in Unix platforms) you should :
        <ul>
        <li>
        Rebuild Apache 1.3 with pthread support (recommanded)
        </li>
        <li>
        Add the LoadFile /usr/lib/pthread.so in beginning of your httpd.conf
        </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        You should also ensure that the linker will be able to locate the apr shared libraries,
        <code>libapr.so</code>, and <code>libaprutil.so</code>, make sure they have been installed
        in linker search locations.
      </p>
      <screen>
        <note>Copy the dso files in the modules location:</note>
        <type>cp jk/build/jk2/apache13/mod_jk2.so /home/apache13/modules</type>
        <note>Copy jkjni.so if you're using JNI</note>
        <type>cp jk/build/jk2/apache13/jkjni.so /home/apache13/modules</type>
        <note>You may have to add pthread library in the httpd.conf:</note>
        <read>LoadFile /usr/lib/pthread.so</read>
        <note>Add mod_jk2 loading in the httpd.conf</note>
        <read>LoadModule jk2_module modules/mod_jk2.so</read>
      </screen>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Apache 2">
      <p>
        In the following example Apache-2.0 is installed in
        /home/apache20/apache40 and the commands are executed in
        the jakarta-tomcat-connectors directory.
      </p>
      <screen>
        <note>Copy the dso files in the modules location:</note>
        <type>cp jk/build/jk2/apache2/mod_jk2.so /home/apache20/apache40/modules</type>
        <note>Copy jkjni.so if you're using JNI</note>
        <type>cp jk/build/jk2/apache2/jkjni.so /home/apache20/apache40/modules</type>
        <note>Add mod_jk2 loading in the httpd.conf:</note>
        <read>LoadModule jk2_module modules/mod_jk2.so</read>
      </screen>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="IIS">
        <p>A pre-built version of the ISAPI redirector server plugin, isapi_redirector2.dll,
        is available under the win32/i386 directory of jakarta-tomcat-connectors distribution.
        You can also build a copy locally from the source present in jakarta-tomcat-connectors
        distribution.<br />The Tomcat redirector requires three entities:
            <ul>
            <li>
            <b>isapi_redirector2.dll</b> - The IIS server plugin, either obtain a pre-built DLL or build it yourself (see the build section).
            </li><li>
            <b>workers2.properties</b> - A file that describes the host(s) and port(s) used by the workers (Tomcat processes). 
                A sample workers2.properties can be found under the conf directory.
            </li><li>
            <b>jk2.properties</b> - A configuration file used by mod_jk2 on the Tomcat side.
            </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
            <ol><li>In the registry, create a new registry key named
            <b>"HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Apache Software Foundation\Jakarta Isapi Redirector\2.0"</b>
            </li><li>
            Add a string value with the name <b>serverRoot</b> and a value which is a full path
            to your Tomcat installation (for example <b>c:\jakarta-tomcat</b>)
            </li><li>
            Add a string value with the name <b>extensionUri</b> and a value of <b>/jakarta/isapi_redirector2.dll</b>
            </li><li>
            Add a string value with the name <b>workersFile</b> and a value which is the full path 
            to your workers2.properties file (for example <b>c:\jakarta-tomcat\conf\workers2.properties</b>)
            </li><li>
            Add a string value with the name <b>logLevel</b> and a value for your log level 
            (can be DEBUG, INFO or ERROR).
            </li><li>Using the IIS management console, add a new virtual directory to your IIS web site.
            The name of the virtual directory must be jakarta. 
            Its physical path should be the directory where you placed isapi_redirector2.dll 
            While creating this new virtual directory assign it with execute access.
            </li><li>
            Using the IIS management console, add isapi_redirector2.dll as a filter in your IIS web site. 
            The name of the filter should reflect its task (I use the name jakarta), 
            its executable must full path to the isapi_redirector2.dll. 
            </li>            
            </ol>        
        </p>
        <p>
        That's all, you should now start Tomcat and ask IIS to serve you the /examples context. 
        Try <a href="http://localhost/examples/jsp/index.html">http://localhost/examples/jsp/index.html</a> for example and 
        execute some of the JSP examples. 
        </p>        
    </subsection>            
  </section>
</document>
